<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>As you vvere, or the new French exercise of the infanterie ballanced with the old.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3917A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223521</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896526</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896526</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133586</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75685)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133586)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2416:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>As you vvere, or the new French exercise of the infanterie ballanced with the old.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>With errata at foot of p. 32.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Drill and minor tactics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Armed forces --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133586:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133586:1"/>
            <p>AS YOU WERE, OR THE NEW FRENCH EXERCISE OF THE INFANTERIE, Ballanced with the Old.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1674.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:133586:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:133586:2"/>
            <div n="introduction" type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ublike warre (one of the effects and ſalaries of ſinne) began to ſhow its ouglie face among the ſonnes of men not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the generall Deluge. The art uſed in it then was certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie rude, bot time and Induſtrie haveing a litle poliſhd it, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie Exerciſe was, no doubt, one of its products, if it was not coetaneous with it. We may therfor after ſo many ages looke for ſome additions to drilling and training, bot not for any new ſiſteme of Exerciſing. To invent new arts is diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill, to adde to them, is feaſible, bot to perfect them not ſo eaſie a worke. Many things are convenient that are not neceſſare, bot nothing is neceſſare, which is not convenient, thogh not at all times, and in all places. So it is that many mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that were uſuall with the Graecians and the Romanes in their exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of warre have beene thought fit to be retaind in ours, which for my owne part I never thought to be neceſſare in the moderne art of warre, and on the other hand, ſome motions frequentlie uſed and practiſd by them, wold have beene perhaps both fiting and needfull for us to have Imitated, and yet we have totallie neglected them.</p>
               <p>There is ſometimes an abſolute neceſſitie to adde to former inventions, and thus it was purlie neceſſare for <hi>Tacticks</hi> and Maſters of the art of warre, to adde to former exerciſes, words of command, for the Dexterous and comelie hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and mannaging Hand-guns, and Harquebuſes, Carabines, Piſtols, and Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, all of which acknowledge Gunpouder to be their Mother, which foure hundreth yeares agoe was not heard to make any noyſe in the world. There be likewiſe many things brought in faſhion by curieous wits, that ſerves more for ſhow then for vſe, and very convenient, I thinke, it ſould be ſo, provided, a neceſſitie of practiſe be not impoſd vpon them. For I am none of thoſe, who thinke that none of the old cuſtomes of warre ſould be alterd, nor am I one of theſe ſevere men, who hate all Novelties, nay I looke on all theſe old ſoldiers, as little better then old fooles, who will not heare of any new Introductions in the art and diſcipline of warre, for no other reaſon, bot becauſe they never ſaw them before, for by this argument, if they had livd three ages agoe, they had rejected the whole art of Gunnerie, concerning all kinds of great Ordinance and artificiall Fireworkes, which ſuceeded the Machines and Engines of warre uſed in the days of old.</p>
               <p>Bot, notwithſtanding of all I have ſaid, I am obligd to tell you, that more then two yeares agoe I red this French Exerciſe in its originall, and had the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133586:3"/>very ſame ſentiments of it. that I ſtill have, theſe for ſome particular reaſons I publiſh now, which I did not at all intend to doe then. I looke vpon it as a very ingenious peece, and the birth of a fertile braine; yet, whether all the ſeverall parts of it be neceſſare, nay, whether they be all convenient, whether they be all for vſe, or for ſhow, or for both, or whether ſome of them be for neither vſe nor ſhow, may by theſe, who are not ſo great lovers of Innovations, as to fall out with old cuſtomes, be both queſtiond and examind, without makeing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſchiſme in the Church, or ſedition in the State. Each ſection of this French Exerciſe, that I looke on as ſingular I ſhall ſet doune apart in the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators words, and immediatlie ſubjoyne an animadverſion to it. Nor ſhall I be troubled, that my Reader reject all my Obſervations as impertinent, becauſe I know, he has as much libertie to adhere to the French Author in all things, as I have taken to my ſelf to diſſent from him in ſome things.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>The Major takes the Muskers, and formes the front of the Battaillon.</p>
                  <p>The Adjutant ought to be at the head of the Pikes, which he draus up in the ſame maner in the reare of the Muskets, at twentie paces diſtance, if he have ground ſufficient.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>IF the Major forme onlie the front of the <hi>Baitaillon,</hi> who formes the Reare, the wings, and the middle of the <hi>Battaillon?</hi> And ſince this Author exeems the Major from the care of the Pikes, I conceave he may with very much caſe forme the whole Bodie of the Muskereers, and perhaps the Author intended it ſo, bot then, I ſay, he hath worded it ill, in calling it the front of the <hi>Battaillon,</hi> for a <hi>Battaillon</hi> is a Bodie conſiſting of ſeverall parts. If any ſay by the front of the <hi>Battaillon</hi> he means, The Musketeers, and by the Reare the Pikemen, I can not be ſatisfied with that anſwere, becauſe the Musketeers of a Regiment drawne up in a Bodie by themſelvs, make a <hi>Battaillon</hi> apart, and ſo doe the Pikemen another <hi>Battaillon,</hi> each wherof hath a front and a reare, till they be joynd in one Bodie, and then they make indeed, bot one <hi>Battaillon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the nixt place, I ſay, An Ayde Major, or Regiment Adjutant is not to be found everie where, thogh the French have him, neither is his Office or his helpe either ſo requiſite or ſo neceſſare in the marſhalling a <hi>Battaillon,</hi> as this ſection of the exerciſe ſeems to import. I am ſo charitable as to beleeve that, there is none of the Field Officers of a Regiment, Colonell, Lieurenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, or Major, bot may forme and draw vp a Regiment or <hi>Battaillon</hi> without helpe, if they doe bot indifferentlie underſtand their charges, and if any of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:133586:3"/>themſelvs be askd the queſtion, I preſume, nothing bot modeſtie will move them to contradict me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>No Companie ſhall enter into the Field, bot in its order, and ſix deepe in file.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>SIr, you ſay well, ſixe deepe in file, in regard it hath beene appointed to be ſo of a long time by two of the moſt Chriſtian Kings, for thogh the French be liberall enough to lend faſhions to other nations, yet they have beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to borrow this from a colder Climate then their owne. But ſince ten deepe was the cuſtome of old, and ſixe deepe is now the cuſtome, how come you to introduce an exerciſe, that can neither be performd by the one nor the other? Doe not you heerby reflect on all theſe famous Generalls both of your owne &amp; other nations, who by makeing their Infanterie either ten or ſixe deepe, bard entrance to this Quarter file exerciſe of yours, which you now bring with ſo much pompe vpon the ſtage? For my part I think, if ever any fancy of it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd their heads, they have lookd on the Theorie therof as loſſe of time, and the practiſe of it as pure fopperie. Nay, who knows, bot ſome of them have thought that to draw up a <hi>Battaillon</hi> ſixteene deepe, and exerciſe it by halfe Quarter files, might be a ſuteable object of an Idle mans ſpeculation. But aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redlie, never one of them conceavd it to be either neceſſare or convenient for this toy of yours, to make ſo great an alteration, as to change the deepth of their <hi>Battaillons,</hi> which in all armies belonging to one Prince, or one State, ſould be conſtantlie one and the ſame. And, Sir, to cry up the ſingularitie of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, I ſhall tell you, that the antient Groecians drew vp their foot <hi>Battaillons</hi> ſometimes eight, ſometimes ſixteene in file, yet had not ſo nimble wits as to exerciſe by quarter files. To come to our own times, The great Earle of <hi>Strafford</hi> orderd his Majeſties Infanterie in <hi>Ireland</hi> to be eight deep in file, which certainlie ſo judicious a perſon, as he was knowne to be, did for good reaſons, if one wherof had beene to exerciſe by quarter files, he had loſt perhaps much of that reputation of militarie skill, which fame hath ſo bountifullie beſtoud vpon him.</p>
                  <p>Sir, in this place, you appoint the Companies to be ſixe deep before they come to the Field, and in another place you order the files to be made eight deepe, when they are in the Field. Bot ſince you muſt exerciſe ſometimes at ſixe deepe, and ſince you will exerciſe ſometimes at eight deepe; I ſhall make no bones to tell you, that it will be much more convenient to exerciſe your foot, one day at ſixe deepe, and another day, at eight deepe, then to put your
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133586:4"/>Captaines to a double labour in one day, firſt to make their Companies ſixe deep, before they come to the Field, and then eight deepe before they goe out of the Field. For to change the deepth of files in the Field purpoſlie for quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter file exerciſe, is not ſo eaſie a worke, as perhaps you at firſt imagine it to be, my reaſon is this. In a file of ſixe deepe you have bot three leading men, theſe be, The Leader of the file, The Leader of the halfe file, and the Bringer up of the file. In a file of eight deepe when you are to exerciſe by quarter files, you have foure Leaders, and foure Bringers up, for divide a file of eight men in quarters, there will be in each quarter a Leader, and a Bringer up, theſe muſt be leaſurlie choſen as fit perſons to obey the words of command of that harſh exerciſe, which needs not be ſo punctuallie done in exerciſes at ſixe deepe. Now the ſtations of theſe files at eight deepe cannot conſtantlie be keepd by the ſame men, becauſe of ſicknes, forloſs, and many other accidents which may withdraw them for a time, and their ſtations being changd, or other men put in their roomes, you ſhall not miſſe to meet with an embarras, the danger wherof yow need not feare in exerciſeing at fixe deepe in file, it being neither ſo knottie nor difficill as the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>The Captaines or Officers muſt leade their Companies with a Pike in their hand. The Lieutenants muſt be at the reare of the Pikes, when there are Enſigneys, and when there are none, they are to place themſelvs at the head of the Pikes, when they are drawne into Battailla.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head type="sub">Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>THe Author tells vs not, whether the Officers ſhall cary their Pikes ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derd, as the Spaniards doe, or comported as the French uſed to doe. Nor ſhall I tell my opinion, whether Pikes, halfe Pikes, Pertiſanes, or Canes be moſt proper for Commiſſionated Officers. Onlie I ſhall deſire the Lieutenants to take notice, that this Maſter, fixes them all with the Pikes, whether in the front or reare of them, makes no matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>The Companies being come to the deſigned ground, ſhall file of one after another, and paſſe vpon the left wing of the Pikes, and in the first place, ſhall leave their Pikes in the Field of the batle, and the Muskets ſhall purſue their march, till they have joyned the front of their Muskets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>ONe of the hardeſt leſſans ever I red. As it is worded, I ſhall never reach the meaning of it. Companies; which the Author himſelf acknowledgeth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133586:4"/>to conſiſt of both Muskets and Pikes, ſhall paſſe on the left wing of the Pikes. <hi>Dura Dictio,</hi> who can underſtand it? Companies, which conſiſt of Pikes and Muskets, ſhall in the firſt place leave their Pikes in the Field of batle, Firſt, a Companie is no more a Companie, bot a part of a Companie, when the Pikes are left behind. Nixt, how can the Pikes be left in the Field of batle, ſince that muſt of neceſſitie be the Field of batle, where both Muskets and Pikes of the whole Regiment are formd in one Battaillon. Bot take head. Muskets ſhall purſue their march, till they have joynd the front of their Muskets. Where are we now? O, for an Interpreter, I am affrayd, The Printer hath wrongd both the Author and the Tranſlator. Muſt Muskets or Musketeers purſue their march till they joyne the front of their Muskets? O Sence, where art Thou? In what corner of this Paragraph hath thou hid thy ſelfe? I am ſure, I cannot find the. Bot leſt we offer to wrong the Author, let vs heare him ſpeake in his owne language, Both in his generall and particular Exerciſe of the Infanterie, he hath theſe formall words. <hi>Les Compagnies arrivants dans le Champ de Battaille, deſileront conſecutivement, &amp; iront paſſer ſur l'aisle gauche des Piques, &amp; auparavant laiſſeront leurs Piques dans le Champ de battaille, &amp; les Mouſquets ſuivront le front des Mouſquets.</hi> It is not in my power to Engliſh this otherwiſe, as the Tranſlator hath done. Yet I wold gladlie be ſo juſt to the Author, as to thinke, his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were this: When the Companies arrives at the place of Battoll, they ſhall leave their Pikes behind at that diſtance ſpoke of, (to wit, twentie paces) and the Musketeers ſhall march, theſe of one Companie after another, on the left hand of the Pikes ſtill forward, till they come to the place appointed by the Major for the front of the Muskets. And when all this is done, we may aske, why may not the Musketeers of each Companie leave their Pikes and march ſtraight in a direct line to the place appointed for them, and not be obliged to march in an oblique line vpon the left wing of the Pikes, but more of this heer-after.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>So ſoon as the last Companie hath joyned the Battaillon, the Adjùtant ſhall file of the Pikes by quarter ranks, to goe joyne the Battaillon, on the ſame front of Muskets on the left wing, and without loſeing time, as ſoone as the laſt quarter ranke is arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, he ſhall face them to the left in Demi ranke, to the left the Muskets, and to the right the Pikes, and by a word of command (March) the Pikes and the Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets ſhall poſſeſſe the ſame ground, after which he ſhall give command <hi>(As you were)</hi> takeing care that in all theſe moveings, a Sergeant ſhall be at the wing of each diviſion to prevent their falſifying.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:133586:5"/>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>NOr is this Paragraph renderd ſo ſmooth, as it ſould be, or, as I thinke, as it might be, for aſſuredlie the Adjutant muſt not face the Pikes by Demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rankes, bot by whole rankes, and the Muskets by the left hand Demiranke, the whole Pikes to the right hand, and the Demiranke of the Muskets to the left hand, that, ſo by the word of command, March, they may interchargablie take vp one anothers place, for ſo I vnderſtand the Author, when he ſays, <hi>It ſera ſaire (a ſcavoir, l'Aide Major) a gauche au Demirang de lagauche des Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, &amp; an droict, aux Picques.</hi> The Adjutant (ſays he) ſhall make the left De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miranke of the Muskets face to the left, and the whole Pikes to the right, and then by a command, march, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>But, let the tranſlation be as it will, To the thing it ſelfe, I ſay, that in form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Battaillon conſiſting of two wings of Musketeers, and one Bodie of Pikes, any of the ordinare ways vſed formerlie ſeemes to me as formall, &amp; more eaſie, as the way preſcrivd by this French Author. And when the Major hath drawne the Musketeers in one Bodie, And the Adjutant the Pikemen in another twentie paces behind the muskets, according to the Anthors direction, I ſhall, by his permiſſion, ſay, the Pikes may joyne the Battaillon of muskets, with ſeuer words of command, in a ſhorter time, and with leſſe trouble and embarras, then by the way mentiond by the Author.</p>
                  <p>I ſay, with fewer words of command, thus. The Author will have the Pikes to march in foure ſeverall Diviſions (for ſo I vnderſtand his quarter rankes) and this requires foure ſeverall words of command, for to everie quarter ranke he muſt ſay, march. When the Pikes have marchd to the left hand of the muskets (for there the Author will needs have them to be) They muſt face to the right hand, and that requires the fifth word of command. Immediatlie after the halfe of the muskets muſt be orderd to face to the left hand, and that is the ſixth word of command. Then the halfe Bodie of muskets, and the whole Bodie of pikes muſt march, or rather countermarch to take vp enterchangeablie one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others ground, that is the ſeventh word, And laſtlie when muskets and pikes have changd their grounds, they muſt be orderd to face, as they were, and that will be the eight word of command. Bot I ſay foure words may ſerve the turne firſt, let the halfe ranks of muskets face to the left hand, that is one, nixt, let that halfe ranke of muskets march, till there be a competent Intervall made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tueene it, and the other Demiranke of muskets, to receave the pikes, that is the ſecond word; thirdlie, order the pikes to march all in one entire Bodie from the reare, and take vp that Intervall, that will be the third word of command; laſtlie, cauſe the forſaid Demiranke of muskets face as it was, and that is the fourth word of command; and then your Battaillon is formd without more words.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:133586:5"/>
                  <p>Secondlie, I ſay, in a ſhorter time, as thus: To march in a whole bodie is a worke of quicker diſpatch by three parts of foure, then to march in foure ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Bodies or quarter ranks, as the Author orders the pikes to doe, before they joyne the musketeers. Secondlie, a bodie greater or ſmaller, will twice as ſoon march twenty paces in a ſtraight and parallel line, then fortie perhaps fiftie in an oblique or croocked line, as theſe pikes muſt doe, which ſtand twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie paces behind the Battaillon of muskets, and muſt march to the left hand of them. Now, the Author in this ſection ſays, without looſing time, therfor it is, that I propoſe a way that looſeth leſſe time, then this way of his.</p>
                  <p>Thirdlie, I ſay, The Battaillon of muskets ſtanding in one Bodie, and the pikes in another twentie paces behind the other, (as the Author appointeth them to be.) The pikes may be receavd in the middle of the Battaillon of mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets with much leſſe trouble and embarras, then by the way preſcrivd by the Author, thus: Let the Demirank of the Battaillon of muskets face and march to the left hand, (leaving the right Demirank ſtanding firme) and ſo make an Intervall, this is done without any embarras at all, nixt let the whole Bodie of the Pikes advance at one time, and take up that intervall, and this is likewiſe done without any embarras. Thirdlie, the Demirank of muskets, which did face and march to the left hand, being commanded to face as they were, doe it alſo without any embarras at all. Bot when the Pikes that ſtand on the left hand of the whole Battaillon of muskets, and the left Demirank of the muskets are orderd to face one to another, and then by a Countermarch to take up one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others ground, there will be ſome ſhouldering, ſome juſtling, and ſome claſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of armes, even among the beſt trained Soldiers, and that I call, Embarras.</p>
                  <p>The French Kings Officers are obliged by this Section to marſhall their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments according to its preſcriptions, and no other way, Bot theſe Officers &amp; Drill-maſters who receave no French pay, may try either this way of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, or the good old way, or a third, if they pleaſe, and then retaine any of them, they find moſt convenient for themſelves, and moſt eaſie for their Soldiers.</p>
                  <p>Laſtlie, This Author requires a Sergant to be at the wing of each Diviſion, to prevent their falſifying. Obſerve here, that a Regiment ſtanding in Battel, there are two diviſions of muskets, and one of pikes; Two Sergants being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to attend each diviſion, will be ſixe that are appointed for that dutie, In my obſervation upon the nixt ſection, we ſhall ſee how the reſt of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gants are diſpoſed of.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>When a Battaillon is formed, the firſt Lieutenant ſhall ſtand in the reare of the firſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:133586:6"/>diviſion of muskets, and the laſt in the reare of the laſt diviſion, an Enſigney in the reare of the Pikes, with one half of the Sergants, to hinder the Souldiers from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſing, or breaking their ranks.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>I Never had ſo ſtrong a conceit of the uſefulneſs of a Lieutenant in a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, or a Lieutenant Collonel in a Regiment, that I need care, where this French Gentleman place the Lieutenants, whether with the Pikes or the Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, In the front or the reare, nor ſhould I be much troubled, if in imitation of a wiſe and a warlike Nation, he ſhould baniſh them for ever out of all his Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taillons; Bot indeed, I am aſtoniſhed to fee him make Lieutenants Ubiquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for in the ſixth ſection of the way to forme a Battaillon, (as I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) he appoints the Lieutenants to be in the reare of the pikes, if there be En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigneys, and in the front of the pikes, if there be no Enſigneys, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſtill with the pikes, either in front or reare whether there be Enſigneys or not, Now in this ſection which I laſt cited, he orders one of the Lieutenants to be in the reare of the firſt diviſion of muskets, and another Lieutenant to be in the reare of the ſecond diviſion of muskets. Can two Lieutenants be with the muskets, if all the Lieutenants be with the pikes, unleſs a Lieutenant can be in two places at one time? If it be ſaid, the Lieutenants are to be with the pikes, when the Battaillon is forming, bot when it is formed, they may be otherwiſe diſpoſed of, to ſhun conteſt, I am content to be ſo charitable (though I ſee no reaſon for it) to beleeve the Author meant ſo, bot then I ſay, why takes he ſo much notice of the firſt and laſt Lieutenants, and tells us nothing where the reſt of them ſhall have their ſtations, whether ſtill with the pikes (which moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bablie he meanes) or ſome more of them then two with the muskets, (which moſt rationallie he ſould have meant) or that he leaves the reſt, except theſe two, to be <hi>individua vaga,</hi> to wander where they pleaſe. And indeed, though he doe ſo with all of them, I am ſure I ſhall not fall out with him for the matter.</p>
                  <p>In the nixt place, I deſire it may be rememberd, that in the eight ſection of the way to forme Battaillons, the Author requires a Sergant to be at the wing of each diviſion, which, in my animadverſion on that ſection, I reckond to be ſixe, in this ſection he requires the halfe of the Sergants to be with an Enſigney in the reare of the Pikes, Now let us ſuppoſe there be in one Regiment ten Companies, theſe have twentie Sergants allowd them, of theſe the Author takes the halfe, to wit ten, and placeth them in the reare of the Pikes, and ſixe on the wings of three Diviſions, this is in all ſixe teene, there remaines then bot foure of the twentie to attend the reare of the Musketeers, which being twice as nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous as the Pikes, makes this Diviſion of the ſtations of Sergants very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionable Sergants formerlie were obliged onlie to attend the wings, Bot
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133586:6"/>if the Author doth allow as he doth, Sergants to be in the reare as well as on the wings, I ſhall agree with him, for I have oft wonderd, why ſo neceſſare an Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer as a Sergant, ſould be pind to the flanks, as I have ſeene too oft practiſd, Bot I will ſtill diſſent from him in allowing ſo many Sergants for the reare of the Pikes, and ſo few for the reare of the Muskets, till he make it appeare, that Pikemen may break their ranks, bot Musketeers cannot,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>The Drums ſhall be placed on the right hand and the left.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>IF he meane on the right and left hands of the whole Battaillon or Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I would gladlie know, what they ſould doe there? I ſould thinke it moſt conſonant to reaſon (not to ſpeake of practiſe) that when a Battaillon, Brigad, or Regiment is formd, everie Officer (among whom Drummers ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narlie are reckond) ſould have his ſtation aſſignd him in that place, where he can doe beſt ſervice, whether they be to fight, or to march, Bot to what uſe Drums ſhall ſerve either on the right or left hands of the whole Battaillon, and in no other place, when they are either to fight or to march, is a thing not ſo eaſilie underſtood. Bot if the Author meane, that Drums ſhall be placed on the right hand and the left, onlie ſo long as the Battaillon is Exerciſing; I ſay, he was obliged to tell us, at what diſtance on the right and left hand the Drums ſould have their ſtations, for I am ſure, The French Drill-maſters will confeſſe, that there be ſome motions of Exerciſe, which will not ſuffer either Drummers or other people to be within a great diſtance of either right or left hand of the whole Battaillon. As when halfe files are commanded either by halfe File-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or Bringers up of whole files to double the front of the Battaillon Entire, or to the right and left hand by Diviſion, when this word of command is obeyd, the Battaillon poſſeſſeth in front twice as much ground as it did before, bot theſe halfe files can not performe this, till they chace the Drums a great way from both the right and left wings of the Battaillon.</p>
                  <p>Bot, before I part with this head of forming a Battaillon, I ſhall take leave, to ſay, that I conceave, The Author hath not ſaid ſo much on it, as he might, at leaſt, not ſo much as he ſould, and conſequentlie that his rules concerning it are Defective, and becauſe I am obliged to give reaſons for my opinion, I offer theſe firſt, he hath not told us, what Companie ſould have the precedencie of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that is, where the Lieutenant Collonels Musketeers and Pikes ſould ſtand, (for I ſuppoſe he allows the Collonels the right hand) where the Majors, where
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133586:7"/>the oldeſt Captaines, where the youngeſt, and where the reſt, that everie one of them may have their due according to their prioritie. This is a point, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is neither cuſtome nor law of warre univerſallie obſerved, it being va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable according to the pleaſure of the Prince or State, who wageth the warre, or of their Generalls who mannageth it. Secondlie, he has not aſſignd to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Officer belonging to the Battaillon their proper ſtations, for thogh it may be ſoone knowne, where the Officers of a private Companie fould ſtand, ſo long as it is a Companie apart, yet when the ſeveral Companies are incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in one Bodie, the ſtations of the Officers are ſenſible changed, as any who never ſaw a Battaillon bot in paper, may eaſilie underſtand. All he hath done in this ſo neceſſare a point, is to tell us, where the Enſigneys, Sergants and Drums, and the Lieutenants ſould be, and that in ſo confuſd and unintelligible a way (as I have demonſtrated) that he might better have ſaid no more of them, then he hath done of the Captaines, and the three Field Officers. Nor doe I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, any man will be ſo litle the Authors friend, as to ſay, he needed not ſpeake of theſe two points, becauſe they are knowne in the French Armies, for by that reaſon he might have held his peace of very many things mentiond by him in his Booke, which were not onlie knowne in <hi>France,</hi> bot in moſt places of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, long before his Grand-father was borne.</p>
                  <p>To ſupport theſe reaſons given for my opinion, I ſhall ſay further, that a Battaillon, Regiment or Brigad (or give it what name elſe you pleaſe) is formd for one of foure reaſons. Theſe are, either to be lookd upon and viewd by a Prince, a General, or ſome great Perſonage, or to fight, or to march, or to Exerciſe. In the firſt caſe it is very proper and convenient, that everie Companie be placed according to its prioritie, and everie Officer have his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aſſignd him according to his Dignitie. In the three laſt caſes, thoſe two points are not onlie convenient, bot purlie neceſſare. And therfor I conclude, a Battaillon is not formd; or not formd as it ſould be, where any of theſe two things are either omitted or forgot. The Author haveing with many niceties formd his Battaillon, as you have ſeene, proceeds thus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>The Generall Exerciſe for the Infanterie. After haveing drawne the Regiment into Battailla, they draw out the files of Halberdeers, which are placed on the wings of the Battaillon by the following commands. Take care, Halberdeers to forme your files on the wings of your Battaillon. To the right and left by halfe ranks draw your files on the wings of your Battaillon, March.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>AFter ſo much pains in this general Exerciſe, in giveing us ſo many motions many old, and many new, to repeate moſt of them (except doubling by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133586:7"/>quarter ranks &amp; quarter files) in the particular exerciſe of the foot, can be done, as I conjecture, for no other reaſon, bot that in the firſt he gives us theſe he thinkes moſt convenient, and in the ſecond theſe he conceaves moſt neceſſare; bot why either the one or other, let us a litle examine.</p>
                  <p>To place ſome files of Halberdeers or Pertiſaners on the flankes of the Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keteers, is no doubt of excellent uſe, for in our ordinarie Battaillons the firemen ly open on their wings to the Impreſſion of any Cavallerie, eſpeciallie Curaſeers, Bot our Author ſould have appointed them to be ſtronglie armed for the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, otherwiſe Piſtolls will reach them, before the Horſe come within reach of their Halberds. Bot, I thinke, he is more to blame, for not telling us, how many files of theſe Halberdeers are needfull: Nor can he be excuſed for giveing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to draw out the files of Halberdeers to be placed on the wings of the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taillon, without telling us from whence, or from what place they ſould be drawn. We know not, for any thing he ſays, where theſe Halberdeers are, Bot ſince he permits us to gueſſe, I conjecture that at firſt they muſt be with the Bodie of the Pikes, if ſo, may it not be asked, whether Pikemen will not ſerve the turne as well, and if that be granted, and the number of the files condiſcended on, they may be ſent from the Bodie to the wings by two commands; firſt, ſo many files of Pikes face to the right, and ſo many to the left. The ſecond, march to the right and left wings of the Musketeers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Then they open the files of the Baettaillon. Take heed to your ſelves in opening your files, that the right hand file ſtir not. To the left open your files to three foot diſtance March, Halt, To the right.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>WHen the Halberdeers have taken their ground on the wings, muſt the files of the Battaillon open? for what reaſon? To what purpoſe? I wold haue thought that the files of Halberdeers being drawn from the Bodie to the wings had left a voyd place, which was neceſſare to fill up by cloſeing the files, bot the opening them is a miſterie, and a greater miſterie to me it is, that they are commanded to open to three foot of diſtance. At what diſtance were they before? perhaps at cloſe order, which ordinarilie is reckond to be one foot and a halfe, Bot this will not ſatisfie thoſe who ſtand ſtronglie for all the Author ſays, in regard neither he nor they will be governd according to antient cuſtome, &amp; therfor I muſt come cloſer up to both him and them, &amp; ſay, The files could not be at one foot &amp; a half diſtance, becauſe the Author orders them to be at 3. foot diſtance in the fourth ſection of forming his Battaillon, where he hath theſe expreſſe words. The Major or Adjutant muſt obſerve that the diſtance of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133586:8"/>files (when they are not exerciſing) is onlie halfe a pace diſtance, bot when they come to handle their armes or doublings, they muſt open to a whole pace; This ſhall not be contradicted by me. Bot in this ſection, which I now examine, the Author contradicts himſelfe, in bidding the files open to three foot diſtance, which preſuppoſeth them to have beene at a cloſer order, and this in the ſection cited by me, he doth not at all admit, That by a pace is meant ſixe foot is cleare by the Tranſlator, who in this ſection interprets that which the Author in French calls halfe a pace, to be three foot. Now, how files who were at no clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer order then three foot, ſhall open to three foot diſtance paſſeth my natural underſtanding. And thogh it ſould be granted to the Author, that he is not obliged to any old forme of exerciſing, yet I think he is bound not to diſagree from his owne forme.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>The Exerciſe of the Musket. Take heed to your ſelves there in the exerciſing your Musket. Lay your right hand on your Musket. Poyſe your Musket. Joyne your left hand to your Musket. Handle your Match, Blow your Match, Cock your Match, Try your Match, Lay your two ſingers on the Pan, Blow your Match, open your Pan, preſent. At this command the Pikes charge. Give fire, withdraw your Armes. At this command the Pikes advance. Take out your Match, returne it to its place, Blow your Pan, Take your Primer, prime your Pan, ſhut your Pan, pas your Musket to the ſword ſide. Take your charger, open your Charger with your teeth, put the powder into the barrel. Draw your rammer, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance your rammer, Shorten your rammer againſt your Breſt, put in your rammer into your Gun, Ram hard, withdraw your rammer, advance your rammer, ſhorten your rammer againſt your breſt, returne your rammer. Joyne your right hand to your Musket, poyſe your Musket, ſhoulder your Musket.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>WHat all theſe commands ſerve for, I doe not know, ſince the moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie one is omitted, both here and in the particular Exerciſe for the foot. And trulie if the French Musketeers forget to charge with ball, as well as this great Drill-maſter hath forgot to give a word of command for it, The moſt Chriſtian Kings Enemies may have a cheape market of moſt of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanterie,</p>
                  <p>In the nixt place, I can obſerve no new precepts for the Exerciſe of either Musket, or Pike, perhaps the former way of uſing or handling of both hath beene altered by the Author, and if ſo, he was obliged to ſet down his directions, and rules how to obey his new way, for without them, his owne Diſciples may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:133586:8"/>differ among themſelves in the explanation of his new fangle way, as much, as <hi>Mahomets</hi> followers, <hi>Haly, Ebubequer, Homer,</hi> and <hi>Oſman</hi> diſagreed in the interpretation of their falſe Prophets new Doctrine.</p>
                  <p>His words for exerciſing the Musket were uſed by the French long agoe, and yet are by all, who have layd aſide the Muskets reſt, (for that requires an alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) which, for any thing I know, is now univerſallie out of faſhion, both becauſe Muskets are made lighter, then at firſt they were, as likewiſe, becauſe uſe (which <hi>Caeſar</hi> calls <hi>rerum Magiſter</hi>) hath made them more mannagable. Bot before I goe further, let me ſpeak a few words of Hand-guns.</p>
                  <p>Though the Musket and Piſtoll have now got the preheminence over all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Weapons both for Horſe and Foot ſervice, yet none of them are of an old invention. It is about 370. years or therby, ſince <hi>Swart</hi> the German Monke found out Gun-powder, the mother of all fire engines, after which in a little Intervall of time followd the invention of the ſeverall kinds of Ordinance, nixt them Harquebuſes of <hi>Croc,</hi> with longer and ſhorter Harquebuſes for horſemen, and foot Soldiers. Muskets were not heard of (as many thinke) till the ſiege of <hi>Regium</hi> in <hi>Italie</hi> 250, years after the birth of powder. Bot for my part, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve they be not ſo old, becauſe I find no mention of them in all theſe great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth of <hi>England,</hi> in the years 1530, 1536, and 1542, nay; nor in that brave Armie of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond of <hi>France,</hi> wherwith he marched in Perſon into Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie to aſſiſt the Dutch Princes againſt their maſter the Emperour, and that was in the year 1550. or therby. And which is more, <hi>Monluc</hi> the famous Mareſhall of <hi>France</hi> in his Commentaries ſpeaks bot of a very few Harquebuſes for every French Companie of foot, and not one word of a Musket in the years 1330, and 1536, the Croſſebow being then much uſed by the French, and the Longbow by the Engliſh. The Piſtoll began to come in faſhion in the raigns of <hi>James</hi> the fourth of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the eight of <hi>England.</hi> Bot to our purpoſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Exerciſe of the Pike. Take heed to your ſelves there, Pikemen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>IN his commands for exerciſeing the Pike, I find litle or no alteration in moſt of his words from theſe uſed before his time, In the way how to obey theſe words, it may be he differ from others, bot he has not told it to us. I ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert to ſome things he hath omitted to tell us, bot before I doe it, it will not be impertinent to ſpeake ſomthing of that ancient Weapon, the Pike.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:133586:9"/>
                  <p>The Pike is ſo old a Weapon, that the ſeverall poſturs of it have beene taught many ages a goe, we have moſt of our words of command for it from the Greekes. The Romanes made litle or no uſe of it. The Graecians in the days of old, did admirable feates with it, the Macedonians farre greater, and in later times, the Switſers have made themſelvs formidable by it. The Graecian Pike for moſt part was eighteen foot long. The Macedonian one, was one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie foot in length. Our Europaean Pikes are ordinarlie reckond to be eighteene foot long, bot in many places they exceed not ſixteene.</p>
                  <p>One hundreth and fiftie years agoe the Infanterie of our moderne Armies conſiſted moſtlie of theſe who were armd with long Weapons, which the French calld <hi>Long-bois,</hi> in which were comprehended, Partiſanes, Hallberds, Two-han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Swords, Axes with long handles, and eſpeciallie Pikes, they who carryed them were ſtronglie armd for the Defenſive, and were called the heavie armed. The Bowmen, Slingers, and Darters were called the light armed, in Latine, <hi>Velites.</hi> Bot Bows, Darts, and Slings, were chac'd away by Harquebuſes, and when theſe began to be numerous, they who carryed them, were reckond to make the fourth part of the Infanterie, as at <hi>Vienna,</hi> when <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>Soliman,</hi> his foot conſiſted of eightie thouſand men, wherof twentie thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand were Harquebuſiers, the other ſixtie thouſand were all armd with long Weapons of ſeverall kinds. Bot after Muskets made a noiſe in the World, they chac'd away Harquebuſes, and they who carryed them challengd the third part of the foot to belong to them, and not contented with that, In a ſhort time, they would be halfe play makers, nor did they ſtop there, for now Univerſallie, Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keteers make two parts of three of the Infanterie, and in ſome places I have ſeene the Musket uſurpe the ſole ſoveraigntie of all Weapons in foot Battaillons, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the Pike abſolutlie, not one wherof I could ſee in many Regiments.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Order your Pike. Charge to Horſe. Draw your Sword. Returne your Sword. Order your Pike, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>THat which the Author calls preſent your Pike, The Tranſlator all along renders it, Charge your Pike, how properlie, I can not tell. That which he ſays here, Charge to Horſe, the originall hath it preſent the Pike to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallerie, and it is like the Author intended not then to charge the Horſe with Pikes, becauſe he immediatlie ſubjoyns, draw your Sword, which could not be done when the Pikemen chargd, Bot my worke is with the Author, not with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:133586:9"/>the Tranſlator. Therfor I ſay, This French Gentleman doth not tell us in what poſture the Pike ſould be preſented to the Cavallerie, or how the Pikemen ſould draw their Swords, both which he was obliged to doe. If Pikes be preſented with both hands, how can theſe who preſent them draw their Swords? Perhaps with their teeth. The antient cuſtome was, to foot their Pikes, and draw their Swords over their left arms, Bot whether this Author, means this or another way, who can Divine, ſince in it, as in many things elſe, he is ſo ſuperciliouſlie reſervd? Practiſe indeed, hath taught that poſture of putting the but of the Pike to the right foot, holding the ſhaft of it with the left hand, and drawing the Sword with the right, to be too weak to endure the Schock of Horſe, eſpeciallie Seus d'armes, and therfor many have thought, that a Bodie of Pikes haveing its ranks and files at cloſe order, preſenting their armes at a ſteadie poſture, without drawing Swords is fitteſt to reſiſt a Cavallerie. Bot, whether, This Gentleman hath brought backe the old cuſtome, or invented a new one, we know not, if he had pleaſd to ſpeake out his mind, any may to preſent Pikes and draw Swords at one time, wold have got followers, as well as other French faſhions doe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Take heed there, the whole Battaillon to preſent your armes. Musketeers make rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. The Pikes charge at the ſame time. To the right, to the right, to the right, to the right, Halfe turne to the right, <hi>As you were,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>THe Author haveing taught us the exerciſe of Musket and Pike, doth at full length teach us Faceings, Doublings, Counter-marches, and converſions, he wold have taught us better, if he had inſtructed us how, and in what manner we ſould obey ſome of his new commands. I ſhall ſay here in the generall, that 64. or 65. years agoe another French Gentleman <hi>Louis de Montgomerie,</hi> Lord of <hi>Carbouſin,</hi> wrote of all neceſſare motions of exerciſe for Bodies of either Pikes or Muskets, or both, which was done, no doubt, by many, before he could draw a Sword, and by many, ſince he went to another World.</p>
                  <p>Bot I ſhall not offer to wrong this Author, with whom I have to doe, to think, he imagind all the motions and evolutions he ſpeaks of, to be neceſſare, it ſeems to me, he thinks not ſo, becauſe, when he hath done with his general Exerciſe, he gives us a particular Exerciſe for the foot, which he calls neceſſare and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare in encounters, Then what are all thoſe mentiond in the general exerciſe and not in the particular one, if they be not neceſſare? Certainlie he aſſerts them to be at leaſt fitting, and convenient. Whether all of them be ſo or not, requires ſome conſideration.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:133586:10"/>
                  <p>The various and diverfieing alterations of the Authors doublings by Leaders of files, Leaders of halfe files, and Bringers up of whole files, by whole rankes, halfe rankes, and quarter rankes, to the front and the reare, of theſe of the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to the wings, and of the wings to the middle (which middle, The Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor renders conſtantlie, The Center, I hope not a Geometricall one) and both of them Inwards, are, in may be, all of them prettie for ſhow, bot not the halfe of them for uſe. As to the conveniencie of them, let it be conſiderd, that thoſe of them that are moſt for uſe, are moſt eaſie for the Drill-maſter to teach, and the Souldiers to learne, wheras theſe that are meerlie for ſhow, are more difficill both to teach and to learn.</p>
                  <p>As to the Exerciſe by quarter files, I ſuppoſe, theſe Officers who underſtand it, or thinke they doe ſo, will find worke enough to inſtruct their Souldiers in it, and certainlie much time will be ſpent, before they make them capable to obey readilie and perfectlie the ſeverall commands, that belong to it. How lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle it ſerves for uſe, may be known by this, that you muſt alter the deepth of your battell, before you can practiſe it, and the Author himſelfe tells you, the Battaillon muſt be eight deepe, the reaſon is cleare, becauſe the quarter of that file, which is compoſd of ſixe men, is one and a halfe, and Drill-maſters muſt not be permitted to devide a man in two halfes. To prove, that this Exerciſe by quarter files can not be made uſe of before an Enemie, thogh he be at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, will be needleſs labour, for I ſuppoſe it will not be denyed by the Author himſelfe or any of his Abettors, yea, I thinke, he tacitlie grants it, when he ſays nothing of it in his particular Exerciſe for the foot, where he ſpeaks of things neceſſare and ordinare in encounters. And yet in former times it hath beene layd downe for a ground, that practiſe before an Enemie is the ultimate end of all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie Exerciſes. The antient Romans (a people that deſerved imitation) exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſd their ſoldierie everie day ſummer and winter, yet everie point of their exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe was not onlie frequentlie bot punctuallie practiſd before an enemie, which made the Jewiſh Hiſtorian <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſay, that the militarie Exerciſes of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans were bloodleſs Battels, and their Battels were bloodie Exerciſes.</p>
                  <p>This exerciſe by quarter files cannot be made uſe of, bot in theſe Bodies, the quarters of whoſe files terminats in an equall number of men, therfor you can not exerciſe by quarter files, when your file is ten deepe, as all the Infanterie of <hi>Europe</hi> was fiftie years agoe, becauſe the fourth part of ten is two and a halfe, nor can you doe it, when your file is ſixe deepe, as moſt, if not all <hi>Europaan</hi> foot now are, becauſe the fourth part of ſixe is one and a halfe, and yet both ten and ſixe are equall numbers. Let it be a rule to thoſe who exerciſe by quarter files, that, That equall number whoſe quarter terminats in an equall number, is a number proper for them, and onlie proper for them, ſuch are, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, 32,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:133586:10"/>36, 40. Bot the nixt equall number to any of theſe will not ſerve their turne, a 10, 14, 18, 22, 26, 30, 34, and 38, becauſe the quarters of all theſe terminates in an unequall and od number, or rather in a number and the halfe of an unite, as the quarter of 14, is 3 ½, the quarter of 22, is 5 ½, the quarter of 26, is 6 ½, and ſo of all the reſt.</p>
                  <p>Theſe who intend to make uſe of this exerciſe for ſhow (for I hope, it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to nothing of neceſſitie) had need to keepe conſtantlie the ſame men in theſe ſame rankes and files, wherin they were, when they were firſt exerciſed that way, for if any of them be changd from their former ſtations, The Drill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter ſhall have a new worke to beginne againe with them. As by example, The firſt and ſecond men in the file make one quarter of it, The third and fourth make the ſecond quarter, The fifth and ſixth make the third, and the ſeventh &amp; eight make the fourth quarter of the file. Now, if the men who have ſtood (it may be) ſixe or ſeven dayes in one and the ſame place of the file have cund ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this abſtruſe Doctrine, that is lecturd to them, doe not change them or their ſtations, If you doe, your former labour is loſt, you muſt beginne againe, becauſe you have neither the Leaders nor followers of quarter files, that you had before. It is not ſo in the old and ordinare commands of exerciſe, the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance wherof is with much leſſe difficultie. And trulie in this quarter-file exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, as the Author deſcrives it, Officers wold not onlie be of a quick apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to underſtand all the hard words of command uſed in it, bot they wold like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have very tenacious memories to retaine them, and theſe who have not, I ſould adviſe to exerciſe by booke, bot then what ſhall become of the Souldiers that cannot read? And thogh they could, yet have no leſſons writ for them how to obey theſe difficill commands. Indeed, I wold have lookd upon it, as a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table act of the Author, and yet no more as what he was bound to doe, both to have ſet down rules, how all his new orders ſould be obeyed, and figures repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting them all to the eye. This, all Tacticks and Maſters of exerciſe before him thought themſelvs obligd to doe, In this he had done himſelfe much right, for then he had not left the rarities of his Invention to be miſunderſtood by the weake apprehenſions of vulgar capacities, who cannot reach his meaning. I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe ingenuouſlie, that after ſome ſtudie, I fancy I have the Ideas of theſe moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or notions (call them which you will) in my head, bot nixt morning I am to ſeek them, nor can I find them, till I find my Booke, and then I muſt ſtudie them <hi>de novo.</hi> Let other Officers, Drill-maſters, and Souldiers have as much braine as they will, ſure I am, they have got worke enough cut out for them. And that Reader of a Countrey Church who durſt not hazard to read the names of <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drach, Meſchah,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> for feare he ſould not pronounce them diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, bot gravelie calld them the three Gentlemen with the difficill names, wold
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:133586:11"/>rather have quitted his office, then adventured either to give or receave theſe hard words of command, of this exerciſe. Take two of them for example. Quarter files in front and reare take care, To the right and left, Quarter files of the front and reare, double your ranks in front and reare upon the quarter files of the Center on the wings, March, march. And within a litle. Quarter files in the Center take heed to your ſelvs? To the right and left, Quarter files in the Center double your ranks in front and reare, on the quarter files of the front and reare, inwards. March, march. Certainlie, theſe words are ſo long &amp; ſo harſh, that they require not onlie a nimble apprehenſion and a readie tongue, bot alſo good lungs, that they may be pronouned with one breath, and with a loud voice. And whether a readie obedience to them be very eaſie, if we can not judge, we may at leaſt gueſſe, and hit right enough.</p>
                  <p>As to the conveniencie of much of this generall exerciſe, I deſire to know, what conveniencie, what delight, what pleaſure in a thing, that is very trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to a Maſter to teach, more troubleſome to a Schollar to learne, and of no uſe at all, when it is both taught and learnd? Exerciſeing of Souldiers ſould render to the lookers on an inward content of mind, to ſee their compatriots expert and readie in feats of armes to withſtand and repell the violence of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Neighbours, that wold diſturbe their peace at home, bot litle content they can have, to heare an Officer command that which puzles his Soldiers ſo in the obedience, that he muſt be glad to bring them to the poſture, As they were. Indeed, I confeſſe, it will be no ſmall matter of ridiculous ſport, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, who love to be merrie with a miſchief, to ſee a deſperate Drill-maſter, ſtampe, ſtare, ſweare, looke like one frighted out of his wits, and behave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like a man ſomething more then halfe mad, when, neither by words of his mouth, nods of his head, geſticulations of his bodie, nor grimaces of his face, he can get his Soldiers either one way or other to obey theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, which moſt mercieleſlie are impoſed on the poor Drill-maſter himſelf to pronounce, without any methood or rules how to teach performance to his Soldiers; Juſt as, that inward ſweet delight, which Spectators expect to enjoy by ſeeing Tragicall and Comicall events of by-gone times repreſented to the life before their eyes, is turnd to a loud and confuſed laughter, when theſe on the ſtage act their parts fooliſhlie, and impertinentlie, notwithſtanding all the endeavors of the Maſter of the play, and the prompter to the contrarie. Bot it will not be amiſſe to examine one or two particulars of this generall exerciſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:133586:11"/>
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Half ranks take care to cloſe with your files. To the right and left Demiranks cloſe to your files, March. Halfe file-leaders take care to double the ranks on the wings in front. To the right and left half file-leaders double your ranks in the wings in front March, march. Bringers up make good your ſiles as you were, march, march. Half Bringers up take heed there. To the right and left, half file Bringers up double your ranks on the wings in the reare, march, march. File-leaders make good your ranks as you were, march, march. Halfe file-leaders take heed there. To the right and left half file-leaders double your ranks in front inward. March, march. Brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers up make good your ranks as you were. Halfe file-bringers up take heed there. To the right and left halfe file-bringers up, double your ranks in the reare inwards, March, march. File-leaders make good your ranks as you were. March, march. Demiranks take heed there. To the right and left by Demiranks regaine your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, march, halt, to the right and left.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>IF any old Drill-maſter had been ſtanding by the Author, when he commanded Demiranks to cloſe to their files, he wold have concluded, that the nixt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand wold have been one of two, either to make a converſion, whole, halfe, or quarter, or for Demiranks to open to their former order. Bot this old Drill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter wold have been much deceived, for he ſould have heard nothing of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, nor ſould he have heard Demiranks orderd to regaine their diſtances, till twelve commands were given and obeyd, Beſides the word, March, fifteene times repeated. In his exerciſe by quarter files, he does worſe, for there, after he hath orderd the files to cloſe by Demiranks. He gives 33. words of command before he orders the Files to take up their former diſtances, beſide the word, March, 47. times repeated. For my part, I am ſo ſhallow, that I cannot ſo much as conceive how a bodie of men can feaſiblie, handſomlie, I had almoſt ſaid poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie obey any one of theſe twelve commands when either Filos or rankes are at cloſe order. The old rules of exerciſe required open order, or open open order, bot antient and approved cuſtomes are too weake barrs to confine this Authors unbounded conceptions, yet I thinke they ſould be limited by his owne rule, which is, that when the Battaillon is exerciſed, The Files ſhall be at ſixe foot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Exerciſe by quarter files. To the right by quarter files double your ranks in front, march. To the left by quarter files double your ranks in the front. To the right by quarter files double your ranks in the reare. To the left by quarter files double your ranks in the rear.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:133586:12"/>To each of theſe commands he ſubjoyns, as you were. Then follows, halfe file-leaders take heed there, To the right halfe file-leaders double your ranks in front, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>WHat a ſtrange ſally is this? Firſt with ſome trouble and ſome loſſe of time to alter the deepth of the Battailla to no other purpoſe bot to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe by quarter files, and before he had given five commands concerning it, to runne full ſpeed backe to the exerciſe by halfe files, which was ſufficientlie done by him before, for in this place you ſhall heare him give theſe ſame commands, and in theſe ſame very words for ranks to be doubled in front and reare by halfe file Leaders, and halfe file Bringers up, that he gave, when the Battaillon was ſixe deepe. Why this repetition? Is it to let us ſee, he can exerciſe by halfe files when the Battaillon is eight deepe, as well as when it is ſixe deepe? Who doubts, bot he can doe it thogh the Battaillon be two and thirty deep? Is not then this exerciſe by halfe files out of purpoſe, and a litle impertinent, when he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Exerciſe by quarter files? And is not an ayrie repetition of theſe ſome things and words he had given us before, a Battologie? Unleſs there be a miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in it, which I cannot comprehend, And yet I ſould thinke, militarie Exerciſes ſould not be miſterious. I wiſh once more, that the Author or ſome of his Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites wold write a Commentarie on this new Exerciſe of his.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Particular Exerciſe for the foot, for things moſt neceſſare, and ordinarie uſed in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters. Take heed the whole Bodie to preſent your armes. Musketeers make readie. The Pikes charge at the ſame time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>I Can hardlie be induced to believe that all that is containd in this particular Exerciſe be neceſſare, much leſſe moſt neceſſare, or if ſome of them be uſed in encounters, I conceave, it muſt be done on extraordinarie occaſions, and not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarlie. Nor doe I imagine the French Generalls will be perſwaded in any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter to double their files by either Demiranks of the wings, or yet Demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranks of the Bodie. If they doe, they have good lucke, if they put not their Battaillons in an inextricable confuſion, then which an enemie can deſire no fairer advantage.</p>
                  <p>As to that, that the Pikes ſould charge at the ſame time, that the Musketeers make readie, the originall hath it, preſent their Pikes, which the Tranſlator, (as I obſervd before) renders, charge, I know not, to what purpoſe, Pikes ſould ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſent, or charge, when the Musketeers are either makeing readie, or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fire, unleſs they be comd within the length of their Pikes of an enemie, nor doe I thinke it convenient they ſould, for it is neither a neceſſare nor an eaſie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:133586:12"/>poſture for Pikemen to keep their Pikes preſented, the whole time they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing towards an enemie, which I ſuppoſe both they and the firemen are bound to doe, thogh all that while the Musketeers are either making readie, or giving fire.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>To the right, double your ranks in front, ranks as you were. To the left, double your ranks in front, ranks as you were. To the right, double your ranks in the reare, ranks as you were. To the left, double your ranks in the reare, ranks as you were.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>THis way of doubling ranks mentiond here is done thus. The ſecond ranke doubles the firſt, the fourth, the third, and the ſixth doubles the fifth for what uſe this doubling ſerves, let theſe tell, who are more in love with it, then I am. Is it neceſſare and uſefull in encounters? I trow not, nor am I bound to take this Gentlemans word for it. But waveing that queſtion, I affirme, The Author hath committed two groſſe errors in this one Paragraph. Firſt by mentioning onlie this way of doubling ranks (after he had promiſd to give us the Exerciſe of foot in things neceſſare and uſefull) he prefers it to any other way of doubling ranks, wheras it may be done with more conveniencie and advantage by making either Leaders of halfe files, or Bringers up of files to double ranks. My reaſon is, becauſe, thogh when by the laſt two ways ranks are doubled, the files of theſe ranks are at a cloſer diſtance, yet the ranks doubled keepe the ſame diſtance they had, bot by this way of the Author, not onlie files are at a cloſer diſtance, bot the ranks doubled are at twice as great diſtance, as they were before, and ſo the more unſerviceable. The truth is, the moſt advantagious way to double ranks is to make the laſt three halfe files by right and left hand double the three rankes that ſtand before them. Entire, or, (as this Author calls it) on the wings, for therby, you not onlie keepe both your ranks and files at the ſame diſtance they were at before their doubling, bot alſo you poſſeſſe twice as much ground in front, as you did before your doubling. His ſecond error is, that he orders ranks to dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the reare, which muſt be done thus. The firſt ranke doubles the ſecond, the third doubles the fourth, and the fifth ranke doubles the ſixth. Aſſuredlie then, the ranks doubled ſtand with their faces to the Drill-maſter, bot the ranks doubling, turne their backs to him, and ſtand ſtill with their backs to him, for againſt this ridiculous poſture, the Author hath provided us with no word of command either before or after the doubling. Bot to ſtrike home, the neceſſitie of doubling ranks in the reare, muſt needs ariſe from the news you have of an enemies approach in your reare, In this caſe, you will reſolve either to leave him,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:133586:13"/>or ſtand and fight him. If the firſt, I pray you, trifle not away your time, in dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ranks either in front, or reare. If the ſecond, that you mind to fight, then, I ſuppoſe, you will face your Battaillon to the reare, whether you doe this by a Demy tour, (which is the beſt way) or by a Countermarch (which is not ſo good) or by a halfe converſion, (which is the worſt of the three) is not the queſtion here. Bot the face of your Battel being changd, that which was your reare is your front, and what was your front is your reare, and conſequentlie your Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor's and Officers muſt change their places and ſtations. If then you thinke it fit, that ranks double, you may doe it, without bidding them double either to front, or reare, for by what I have ſaid, you may ſee, that ranks muſt all wiſe double to the front, bot never to the reare. If you be pleaſe, to conſider this rightlie, you will perhaps conclude with me, that all the Authors doublings of ranks in the reare, either by this may preſcriv'd in this ſection, or by Leaders of halfe files, or Bringers up of files (wherof he ſpeaks in his generall exerciſe) are not onlie needleſs, uſeleſs, and inconvenient, bot redundant, to call them no worſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>The whole Bodie take care to Countermarch. To the right by ranks Countermarch, March, halt to the right. To the left by ranks Countermarch. March, Halt, to the left.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>WHy not a Countermarch by files as well, as by ranks? The one is as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſare everie bit, as the other. And if he had ſaid, that neither the one nor the other was neceſſare, or yet ordinarlie uſed in encounters, I ſould not at all have contradicted him. Bot the Author in his generall Exerciſe ſpeaks of Countermarches by files, as well as by ranks: So doe ſome others who write of exerciſing, bot I wiſh that ſeeming difference were expunged out of all their Books, for it does bot puzle a young Soldier when he hears or reads of two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Countermarches, one by files, and another by ranks, and if his judgement be not ſubtiler then mine, he will never diſtinguiſh them. And indeed they are bot one thing, files cannot countermarch bot ranks muſt doe it too, nor can ranks countermarch, bot files muſt doe it likewiſe. Imagine a regiment of a thouſand men drawne in battell on a Field, wheron they may march a hundreth in breaſt, That Bodie is drawne up ten deep in file, and ſo there are one hundreth files, and ten ranks, It were ſuperfluous, nay, ridiculous for the Colonell of that regiment, to bid the ten ranks march, or yet the hundreth files march, becauſe the one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not move, but the other muſt move alſo. It is the very ſame thing in a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>march. And therfor in exerciſing, Officers ſould ſay no more, bot, To the right,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:133586:13"/>or, To the left hand, Countermarch, without mentioning either file, or ranke.</p>
                  <p>Countermarches in the dayes of old, were on ſome occaſions thought uſefull, till the force of Gun-powder made the performance of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an enemie dangerous, and conſequentlie, the command for it, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Impertinent. The old <hi>Graecians,</hi> and other nations too, made much uſe of them, in their bodies of foot, which were ſometimes eight, very oft ſixteene deepe, as alſo in their bodies of Horſe, which were foure, five, eight, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ten deepe. There were three kinds of thoſe Countermarches, The <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donian,</hi> The <hi>Laconian,</hi> and the <hi>Perſian,</hi> which was alſo calld the <hi>Choraean.</hi> All theſe three are ſtill uſed in our <hi>Europaean</hi> Exerciſes, bot ſeldome or never in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters for any thing I ever faw or heard, till I read it in this Author. The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ways how all theſe three Countermarches are performed, are known well enough to ordinare Drill-maſters. Bot this Frenchman ſpeaks bot of one kind, nor doth he tell us, of which of theſe three ſorts it is, or if it be of a fourth of his own finding out, and therfor we know not, whether by his Countermarch, He will have us to winne ground, to looſe ground, or keep the ground we have.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Take heed to make a quarter Converſion, To the right a quarter converſion. March, Halt, To the left a quarter converſion. March, Halt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>WE muſt ſuppoſe, when theſe commands were given the files and rankes were at ſixe foot diſtance, for ſo the Author will have the Battaillon to be when it is exerciſed. Bot why he doth not order both ranks and files to cloſe to a nearer diſtance, before he command them to make their quarter converſion, I doe not apprehend. I know the practiſe of others in doeing it, will be no rule for him, bot I wiſh, he had given us a rule how to doe it convenientlie and handſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie at ſo open a diſtance, which to me ſeems ſo unfeaſible, that I conceave the bringing both rankes and files to ſome cloſer order then ſixe foot wold be very needfull, before the converſion be commanded, What neceſſitie the Author hath found, to uſe either halfe, whole, or quarter converſions before an enemie, or in what place of the World they are ordinarlie uſed in encounters, I cannot devine, till he informe us, what ever-uſe may be made of them in exerciſes, I think, they may be with no diſadvantage forborne, when an enemie is neare. This is that Motion which our Scots Drill-maſters uſed to call, The great turne, The Engliſh tearmd it properlie enough, To wheele your Battel, The Dutch, <hi>Swenget euch.</hi> Whether it be more proper for the horſe then for the foot, being it may be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:133586:14"/>performd in farre ſhorter time and with much leſſe trouble with the firſt, then with the laſt, ſhall not be debated heere.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall in this place take occaſion to tell you in few words the opinion of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther French Author concerning Faceings, Doublings, Countermarches, and Wheelings. That is, <hi>Louis de Montgomerie Sieur of Carbouſin,</hi> (whom I once mentiond before) he was a Couſine of that famous <hi>Count de Montgomerie,</hi> (whoſe ſad fate and not fault it was, to kill his Maſter <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond of <hi>France</hi> at juſting) A great Captaine this <hi>Louis</hi> was, and had ſerved long under a farre greater Captaine and a great King too, <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>France,</hi> I ſhall ſpeake firſt of Wheelings. Before you make your converſion, ſays <hi>Montgomerie,</hi> you muſt cloſe your files and your rankes, beginning with the files, and when you have made your converſion, and wold open them to their former diſtances, you muſt begin with the ranks, whether they be to open to the front or the reare, and then with the files, whether they be to open to the right or the left. As to face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, he ſays, it is enough to face to the right hand, or right about, to face to the left he conceaves may make ſome diſorder, becauſe of the Soldiers Swords. Concerning doublings, He thinks if ranks and files be taught to double to the right hand, it is ſufficient, for he holds it not neceſſare for ranks or files to dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the left, or to double ranks by halfe File-leaders, or Bringers up, or yet to uſe countermarches and converſions. Yet concludes, it is in the diſcretion of the Commander to uſe them all, or none of them as he pleaſeth. His words are <hi>Cela, neantmoins, demeure a diſcretion.</hi> It is to be obſerved, that this <hi>Montgomerie</hi> had ſeene the Warres of the Low-countreys, when they were hotlie mannaged by the renouned Captains, <hi>Maurice</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> for the Eſtates, and the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> and Marques <hi>Spinola,</hi> for the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi> And in theſe times, martiall Exerciſes frequentlie reducd to practiſe were in Vogue, The Netherlands being indeed Schooles of warre.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Take notice all. Order your armes. The Pikemen reſt their Pikes on the ground.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>THe French word is, <hi>Repoſes vous ſur vos Armes.</hi> Reſt upon your Armes. The Tranſlator renders it, Order your Armes. The propereſt Engliſh word he can give. Bot trulie I think the French word more proper then the Engliſh one, and the hie Dutch word as proper as any of them, which is <hi>ſtellet euer gevehr bey den rechten fus.</hi> Set your Armes by your right foot. Bot, order your Armes, (to ſpeake ſtrictlie) is too generall a word to denote that ſpeciall poſture which it ſould import, for there is no poſture either of Musket or Pike, which ſould not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:133586:14"/>be done orderly, &amp; a Pike, either ſhoulderd, ported, or comported, ſo it be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomlie done, is a Pike ordered, as well as when the but of it is ſet on the ground. Bot as in this, ſo in ſeverall other motions, I find a penurie and defect of words, which makes ſome of them ſignifie the thing intended very improperlie, This may be obſerved in the French, in the hie and low Dutch, as well as in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh. In all your doubling of ranks by halfe File-leaders and Bringers up, and doubling of files by halfe rankes, the things intended are not fullie nor well enough expreſd by theſe words which were invented and are ſtill uſed for them. As by example, when you ſay, Bringers up of files double your ranks to the right hand, this word ſtrictlie and properlie imports, that you ſould make the rankes double the number, or twice as many as they were, and conſequentlie, ſince they were ſixe before, you ſould by that command, make them twelve, Bot when the word of command is obeyd according to the uſuall way, the very contrare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, for wheras they were ſixe ranks before, they are made to be bot three, the number of men in each of the three formoſt ranks is indeed doubled, bot the ranks themſelves are made feuer. It is the ſame thing in the other languages I ſpoke of. And ſuppoſe, you are exerciſing a Bodie of twentie files, you will ſay, halfe ranks to the right hand double your files. If a man, who never had ſeene any of theſe exerciſes before, were ſtanding by you, he wold aſſuredlie think, you intended to make your twentie files, fortie, bot he ſhall ſee juſt the contrare, when he perceaves that by the performance of that command, your twentie files are made bot ten, The number of men in everie one of the ten files on the right hand are indeed doubled, bot the files themſelves are made feuer by halfe, And as to this motion, I laſt ſpoke of, I believe, it wold be more proper to ſay, halfe ranks double the ranks on your right hand, for therby, indeed, the ranks which ſtand on the right hand and were bot ſixe, are made really twelve, and that is the double number of ſixe. If you pleaſe to conſider it a litle, I believe, you will find it to be ſo.</p>
                  <p>Now, when we ſay, Order your armes, The Souldiers ſet the buts of them on the ground, the Pikemen hold their Pikes in their right hands juſt againſt their right ears, The Musketeers lay their right hands on the barrills of their Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, and ſo both of them leane on their armes, and all leaning is repoſe, therfor it is, that I thinke, Reſt on your armes, is more proper then, Order your armes, and, ſet down your armes at your feet, more proper then any of them. Bot I doe not offer to introduce either new things or new words.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Lay down your armes. The Pikemen ſticke their Pikes between their two legs.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:133586:15"/>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>BOt, if the ground be ſo hard, that you cannot ſticke your Pikes in it, as in a dry ſummer, and a froſtie winter it will unqueſtionablie be, I ſuppoſe you may lay your Pikes on the ground, bot if you can ſtick them, it will be more handſome, and have the braver ſhow. Bot I miſtake the French language, if in the originall which I read, it be not, lay down your Pikes on the ground between your feet. When Pikemen were formerlie orderd to lay down their Pikes, they were taught by a turne of the right hand to lay the buts of their Pikes levell with the out-ſide of their right foot, bot now that <hi>Monſieur</hi> will have us to lay them between our feet, or ſtick them between our legs, let it be ſo, we need not fall out with him for the matter,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Be readie to goe, <hi>a la paille. A la paille.</hi> Which they are to doe when the Drum beats a charge, and are to return, when the Drum beats againe, with their Swords in their hands, and holding them above their heads when everie one is returnd to his place, and when they are returned. Returne your Swords, handle your Armes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>WHat a fanfare is all this? To what purpoſe all this glancing ſhow? what can the buſineſs be? Before this peece was Engliſhed, I read in the French originall, <hi>A la paille,</hi> bot did not know what it meant in exerciſe, bot was hopefull, The Tranſlator wold have helped me, Bot in him I meet againe with, <hi>A la paille,</hi> and with no Engliſh for it. So both the Author and the Tranſlator leave us to our conjectures. For my part, I thinke it is probable, he intended no more bot what is uſuall in exerciſes, to permit the Soldiers, after they had layd down their armes, to goe recreate and refreſh themſelves, under the name of, <hi>a la paille,</hi> and on the beating of the Drum, to returne with drawn Swords to their other armes. Secondlie, <hi>A la paille,</hi> in French, is as much, as, To the ſtraw, is in Engliſh; therfor it may be, he intended, that, when the Battaillon is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campe, and the watch is ſet, and the Regiment hath layd down their armes, The Soldiers are commanded to goe look for ſtraw, and ſticks, for hutting and fuell, And while they are about that worke, if the Drum beate, they are to draw their Swords (in caſe of a ſudden attack) and therwith defend themſelvs, till they get back to their other armes. If neither of theſe two conjectures of mine pleaſe you, you may, (if you thinke it worthie your labour) gueſſe your ſelf, the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to doe it, can be denyed to neither you nor me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:133586:15"/>
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>All ſorts of change of fileings. Take care in all changeings of filings, that the ſiles be of even number, and if there be found any ſupernumerarie files, let them be formed into ranks in the reare of the Diviſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>IN the firſt place, what this Gentleman means by ſupernumerarie files in the plurall number, I do not underſtand, for I conceave, in the greateſt Battaillon that ever was, or yet can be fancied to be, there will be bot one odd file, and why that one od file ſould be called ſupernumerarie (even in the ſingular num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) I know not, od or uneven it may be, bot ſupernumerarie it can not be, for I doe not beleeve that any of the French Captains entertains more Soldiers then theſe the French Kings allows them wages for. And if they have no ſupernume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie Soldiers, they will have no ſupernumerarie files; As litle doe I underſtand why od files (if there were any) ſould be made ranks in the reare, for by that mean you ſhall increaſe the number of your ranks (which ſould be conſtantlie and perpetuallie the ſame) and conſequentlie adde to the deepth of your Battail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, which muſt not be permitted you or any under the Prince, or his Generall. Suppoſe you have one od file (which may frequentlie fall out) if you make a ranke of it in the reare of a Diviſion, then you make that Diviſion ſeven deepe, wheras it ſould be bot ſixe. Sure there is leſſe hurt and leſſe diſorder in an od file, then in an od ranke. If the Author had ſaid, If there be any od men in any of the Companies let them all be caſt in the reare of the whole Battaillon, and make files of them, he had (to my ſence) have ſpoke reaſon, yet no more then very or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie Officers have both ſpoke and practiſd before him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>Manner of fireing. The best way of fireing, is by rank, when you wold fire in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell line with the Enemie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>YEs, To fire by rank is not alone the beſt, bot the onlie way of fireing, if the Enemie be either in your front or your reare. Bot if he be on either of your flanks, you are to face him by theſe files that are neareſt to him, and then you are to fire likewiſe in a parallell line with the Enemie, and yet in this caſe, the Author muſt permit us to fire by file, and not by ranke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>For this purpoſe to doe it with leſſe trouble, it is good to doe it ſtanding firme your ground, without any motion, ſave that, of making the five firſt ranks kneele, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:133586:16"/>let the ſixth be the firſt that fires, then the fifth riſing up, does the like, and ſo the reſt in order.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>I Have ſeen three ſeveral ways how ranks fire ſucceſſivelie, not to ſpeak of fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by three ranks together, the firſt kneeling, the ſecond ſtooping, the third ſtanding, which is not uſed bot at a dead lift. The firſt is, when the firſt ranke hath fired, The Musketeers divide themſelves in two parts, the one half march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by the right, the other by the left hand to the reare, where they are againe by their Officers marſhald in one rank. This way is troubleſome, eſpeciallie if the rank be numerous, as in all great Battaillons ranks are, yet it hath been ſo antient a cuſtome in the armies of the Eſtates of the United Provinces of the Low-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, that I ſaw it practiſd in the year 1659. by the Eſtates Guards at the <hi>Hague.</hi> The ſecond way is, when theſe who have fired, turne to the left hand, &amp; marches down to the reare between that file wherof they were members, and the nixt file to it, This hath farre leſſe trouble in it, and thogh it can convenientlie enough be done, when the Enemie is in front, yet it is moſt proper, when he is in your reare. The third way is, when the firſt rank having fired, ſtands ſtill, the ſecond advanceth ſixe foot before the firſt, and fires, and ſo the reſt ſucceſſivelie. This according to my weak judgement, is the beſt, and hath leaſt embarras in it, bot onlie can be uſed, when your Enemie is in your front, obſerve, that by all theſe three ways, wherof I have ſpoke, you gaine ground.</p>
                  <p>This fourth way which our Author preſcrivs ſeems to me to have two incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies inſeparablie joynd with it. The firſt is, you onlie keep the ground you have, bot gaines none, and in the keeping it, five parts of ſixe of your fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men look like ſupplicants, and not like Combattants. The ſecond inconvenience is, that unleſs your Souldiers by long practiſe be habituated to this New Mode, theſe who kneel may readilie be more affrayd of the bullets of their fellows who ſtand behind them, then of theſe of the Enemy who are at a farre greater diſtance before them, for the nearer danger is, with the more ouglie and dreadfull aſpect it looks. This fear (which is naturall to man) may make Musketeers ſlow to riſe from their kneeling poſture, and when they are up, too ſlow to give fire. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this, the Author gives us no rule how ranks ſhall fire, if an enemie be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, it ſeems, he conceaves Victorie is ſo entaild to his Maſters armies, that they need not provide for a retreate, for if an enemie chance to be in their reare, I ſuppoſe none of their ranks muſt kneele, unleſs it be to beg quarter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>All the ranks, before the skirmiſh renues, muſt be cloſed up to ſixe foot diſtance.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:133586:16"/>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>THe French Original hath it, <hi>deux pas,</hi> two paces. I doe not thinke the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor meant two paces, each of them of five foot, ten foot is too great a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance between ranks of Musketeers. I ſuppoſe he intended two ordinarie ſteps, and the Tranſlator hath done well to make them ſixe foot. Bot why, cloſe up to ſixe foot diſtance? were they ever at a greater diſtance? I believe, not. I will once more put the Author in mind of his own rule concerning diſtances given by him in the fourth ſection of the forming his Battaillon, in which he orders the Major or Adjutant to obſerve, that the due diſtance of files (when they are not exerciſing) is onlie half a pace diſtance, bot, ſays he, when they come to handle their armes or doublings, they muſt open to a whole pace. The like, certainlie, he meant of ranks. In marching, ſixe foot of diſtance between ranks of Pikemen is neceſſare, becauſe the length of a Pike from a mans ſhoulder to the but requires no leſſe, Musketeers in marching requires not ſo much, bot to keep a Decorum, they muſt keep alike diſtance with the Pikes. Since then the Author hath not told us, when rankes either were or ſould be at a greater diſtance then ſixe foot, and ſince other Tacticks have requird no greater diſtance, why ſould ranks, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the skirmiſh beginne (ſays the Author) renue (ſays the Tranſlator) uloſe up to ſixe foot diſtance? And till it be explaind, to me it is unintelligible.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="drill">
                  <head>FRENCH AUTHOR.</head>
                  <p>When they file of on a Bridge before an Enemie after the looſe men have paſſed, The Battaillon muſt be filed of by rank, by the Center.</p>
                  <p>They muſt make quarter Converſions, and half Converſions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="response">
                  <head>Animadverſion.</head>
                  <p>WHy theſe two commands are joynd ſo cloſe together, I ſuppoſe, be onlie known to the Author, and ſome few of his friends to whom he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veald the miſterie. Whether muſt they make theſe converſions, before they paſſe the Bridge, or upon the Bridge, or after they have paſd the Bridge? A very hard matter to doe it, I thinke, in any of the three places, thogh no enemie were near, and yet here it muſt be done before an enemie. If it be anſwerd, that this command for converſions is generall, &amp; hath no relation to the paſſing a Bridge, then, I ſay, The Author plac'd it ill here, Its proper place had been where he ſpoke of converſions both in his generall and particular exerciſe. What hath converſions to doe with paſſing a Bridge?</p>
                  <p>I have now given the reaſons of my diſſent from ſome things of this French
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:133586:17"/>way of exerciſing the Infanterie. Notwithſtanding whereof I think the Authors invention is to be commended, and I ſould have imagined, that moſt of his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties had been practiſd onlie within the walls of <hi>Paris,</hi> or among the traind Bands of <hi>France,</hi> if there be any there, if the title page of the Book had not told me, they are practiſd in the armies of his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty. Yet for all that, I am of the opinion that ſince the time the Author wrote this peece, to this very day, the French Kings armies have been ſo hotlie imployed, that they have had bot litle leiſure to make uſe of all his new motions. The Author might, if he had pleaſd have made his Battaillon ſixteen deepe, as well as eight, and therby not onlie have drilld it by quarter files as well, if not better, bot alſo have imitated the Macedonian <hi>Phalanx,</hi> which was conſtantlie compoſd of ſixteen ranks, and ſo have repreſented to his ſoldiers the forme, diviſions, and ſubdiviſions of that Battaillon.</p>
                  <p>And, becauſe many of his motions are meerlie for ſhow, and ſince for ſuch a trifle, as is that exerciſe by quarter files, he thinks the deepth of a battel may be changed he might have caſt his Battaillon in a Wedge, in a Rhombe or Diamant, in a Globe or Ring, or in a Saw. And ſo have repreſented to his Spectators, the Figures of Battells uſed by the Antients, which to my apprehenſion, wold have been more delightfull to behold then any of his new Evolutions.</p>
                  <p>And once more, if the deepth of Battaillons may be alterd, as the ſeverall fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes of Drill-maſters lead them, they may, if the Regiment conſiſt of a thouſand, or a thouſand twentie four men (as many of our moderne Regiments doe) order their files to conſiſt of two and thirtie men, and ſo their Battaillon ſhall be ſquare of men, and with ſome other rules of the ſquare root, they may make Battaillons ſquare of ground, doubled Battaillons, and Battaillons large of front, the art wherof everie Drill-maſter knoweth not, and yet the ſight and opening up the uſe of theſe (thogh now out of faſhion) wold be of more profit and advantage to an attentive Soldier who minds his buſineſs, and of more pleaſure and delight to the curieous Beholder, then any new thing any of them can ſee in this exerciſe. Bot it will perhaps be anſwerd me, that all theſe things I have mentiond, are old, and this Exerciſe is new, and Novelties, without all peradventure, pleaſe beſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>P. 17. l. 11. for <hi>ſens,</hi> read, <hi>S'ens.</hi> P. 17. l. 15. for <hi>may,</hi> read, <hi>way.</hi> P. 20. l. 29. for <hi>methood,</hi> read, <hi>method.</hi> P. 23. l. 18. for <hi>files of theſe ranks,</hi> read no more, <hi>bot files.</hi> P. 24. l. 11. for <hi>pleaſe,</hi> read, <hi>pleaſed.</hi> P. 24. l. 13. for <hi>leaders of half files,</hi> read, <hi>leaders of files.</hi> P. 24. l. 14. for <hi>brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers up of files,</hi> read, <hi>bringers up of half files.</hi> P. 31. l. 17. for <hi>vloſe,</hi> read, <hi>cloſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:133586:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
